
cat <FILENAME> "returns file contents"
ls "returns directory contents"
history "returns previous commands"
ls --all "returns all files including the ones that start with . i.e.configuration or caching files etc.."
ls -a "same as above i.e. shows hidden files
ls -l "provides long listing of file that includes filesize, whether it is a file or a directory(directories start with d, files with -), last modified time, and filename
Ctrl + R "returns previous commands"
Tab "Autocompletes filenames"
Tab Tab "Provides similar names that are hindering autocomplete"
wc <FILENAME> "returns the number of lines, words, bytes, filename in a file"
diff <FILENAME1> <FILENAME2> "compares two files for differences"
man <COMMAND NAME> "opens a description of the command, all the parameters described in [ ] are optional, parameters are case sensitive, we need to press q to exit"
rm -rf/ "rm stands for remove files, -r is for recursive i.e. it deleetes whole directories, -f is for force which stops Linuxx from confirming file deletion with the user)
uptime  "uptime gives a one line display of the following information.  The current time, how long the system has been running,  how  many  users  are
currently  logged  on,  and the system load averages for the past 1, 5,and 15 minutes."
Ctr + C "sends an interrupt signal to stop the curreent shell program"
bc "calculator program. Exit by either typing quit or presssing Ctrl+D"
Ctrl+D "stands for end of input and tellsthe program that no more input is coming)
less <FILENAME> "shows text from file one page at a time. Once inside less, D or Space to scroll down 1 page, U to scroll up 1 page. Type line number and hit enter to go to a line. To search press /text_to_search(Case sensitive). To go to next occurrence of word press ssmall n, to go to previous occurrence of thee word press capital N. Press q to exit less"
nano <FILENAME> "opens nano which is a terminal based text editor and allows you to edit it. Useful because nano is running on the remote machine and you don't have to download the file to your PC to eedit it"
^ stands for Ctrl key
pwd "prints path of working directory
curl <URL> "downloads from a url
fc <FILENAME1> <FILENAME2> "compares two files


